<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Section 7 Livy: Hannibal Crosses The Alps</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>s6.xml</url>
			<text>Hannibal crosses the Alps: Section VI</text>
		</link>
		<link>
			<url>s8.xml</url>
			<text>Hannibal crosses the Alps: Section VIII</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<line>
		<number>1</number>
		<latin>fessis taedio tot malorum nivis etiam casus, occidente iam sidere Vergiliarum, ingentem terrorem adiecit.</latin>
		<english>A fall of snow, seeing as the constellation of the Pleiades was now setting, added considerable alarm to the soldiers, who were tired from the fatigue of so many hardships.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>ingentem terrorem: </main>
				<text>The snow makes the path(s) invisible. Sheer fatal drops and crevices are now unseen hazards and this is terrifying to already very tired and scared soldiers.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Setting of the Pleiades: </main>
				<text>oaaidente sidere (with the constelation setting) is an ablative absolute</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Vergiliae: </main>
				<text>"ver" is the latin for 'spring'. These stars appeared in Spring, but in this passage they are now setting at the end of the Sailibn Season - more dangeroud to travel. This would add to the fear of the men.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</line>
	<line>
		<number>2</number>
		<latin>per omnia nive oppleta cum signis prima luce motis segniter agmen incedered pigritiaque et desperati in omnium vultu emineret</latin>
		<english>When the column of march was progressing slowly forward through everything covered with snow, with the standards having men moved at dawn, and when the hopelessness and desperation was shining forth on the face of all men,</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>omnia oppleta: </main>
				<text>everything is covered with snow - a complete white-out - gives them no clues as where to step (travs: "all covered")</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>signis motis: </main>
				<text>an ablative absolute (with the standards having been moved). The standards are the important symbols of the army - when they move, so does the army. Using a part of something to imply a whole is called synedoche</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>segniter, pigrita et desperato: </main>
				<text>Livy uses this vocab of depression to build a negative "semantic field". The mixture of fatigue with fear will produce an overwhelming feeling.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>omnia, omnium: </main>
				<text>This is a poolptoton: a repeated word in a different form(s). Here, the polyptotonic repetition serves to emphasise the pervasive nature of the desperation that all the troops are feeling in all the parts of the army,</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>vulta eminerent: </main>
				<text>the desperation "shines out" from the focus of teh soldiers - this means that the helplessness would be very obvious from their facial expressions.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</line>
	<line>
		<number>3</number>
		<latin>praegressus signa Hannibal in promunturio quodam, unde longe ac late prospectus erat,</latin>
		<english>Hannibal, having progressed past the standards to a particular viewpoint, where the view was far and wide</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>praegressus: </main>
				<text>a Perfact Active Participle from a deponent verb. Hannibal goes past the standerds, and seperated himself from the army on an outcrop of rock, and ...</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>in promunturio: </main>
				<text>On an outcrput -> Hannibal has a good sense of the dramatic/impactful (making a good speech - good leader). If you are goinf to inspire your troops you need to be able to capture their attention - part of leadership</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</line>
	<line>
		<number>4</number>
		<latin>consistere iussis militibus Italiam ostentat subiectosque Alpinis montibus Circumpadanos Campos, moeniaque eos tum transcedere non Italiae modo sed etiam urbis Romanae;</latin>
		<english>... having ordered the soldiers to stopm he, pointed out to Italy and the lands of the Pos Valley at the foot of the Alps; and he told them that they were at that moment not climbing over only the walls of Italy, but also of Rome  itself.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Circumpadanos Campos: </main>
				<text>these are the gentle, fertile plains which surround the River Po in Northen Italy. A beautiful, calm place which would have looked like the Garden of Eden to the exhausted soldiers</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>ostentat: </main>
				<text>the graphic use of the present tense helps to bring the reader into this dramatic moment as Hannibal shows his men what they have achieved and what lies in store for them (... Po Valley ...)</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Moenia: </main>
				<text>Hannibal uses a similie - he compares the Apls to the defensive walls of Italy thus illustrating to his men that they have conquered Rome's defences in crossing the mountains - lift their spirits</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</line>
	<line>
		<number>5</number>
		<latin>cetera plana, proclivia fore; uno aut summum altero proelio arcem et caput Italiae in manu ac potestate habituros</latin>
		<english>He [Hannibal] said that the rest of the terrain would be flat or downhill; and that after one or, at the most, two battles they would have in their hands and hold in their power the citadel and capital of Italy</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>plana, proclivia: </main>
				<text>flat, downhill - the easy terrain vocab juxtaposes, and the plosive consonants perhaps reflecting the puffed-out soldiers, will be able to now breathe easier</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>aut summum altetro: </main>
				<text>Hannibal doesn't promise "one more battle" - he is honest with his men about what they can expect. Honesty brreds trust and is an admirable leadreship quality</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>arcem et caput Italiae, manu ac potestate: </main>
				<text>These rheutorical couplings adding emphasis to how much the army has to gain for persevering for a little longer (doesn't need to have both, but adds emphasis).</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</line>
</page>