<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Aeneid: Lines 506-525</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>526-543.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 526-543</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<section>
		<number>1</number>
		<note>Lines 506 - 508</note>
		<latin>Fositan et Priami fuerint quae fate requiras. // urbis uti captae casum convolsaque // vidit limina tectorum et medium in penetralibus hostem,</latin>
		<english>Perhaps you may also ask what was the fate of Priam. When he saw the fall of the captures city, the entrances of the houses torn apart and the enemy in their midst in the inner chambers,</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Collapse of the City: </main>
				<text>The cacophony of the alliteration of "c" emphasises the din of the collapsing walls</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Rhythm: </main>
				<text>Line 507 is mostly spondaic, (slow) as Priam watches with a heavy sadness at what is happening to Troy. Compared to 508, which is dactylic, reflecting the rampaging Greek army as they smash into the inner chambers of the palace</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>2</number>
		<note>Lines 509 - 511</note>
		<latin>arma diu senior desueta trementibus aevo // circumdat nequiquam umeris et inutile ferrum // cingitur, ac densos fertur moriturus in hostes.</latin>
		<english>... the old man vainly puts on his shoulders, which were trembling with age, weapons to which he had long been unaccustomed, girds on his useless sword and, doomed to die, rushes into the closely packed enemy.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Q: How does Virgil emphasise the futility of Priam's actions?</main>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>1) </main>
				<text>His age and weakness is highlighted by "senior", "trementibus" and "aevo". He is way too old to fight.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>2) </main>
				<text>"Nequiquam" (in vain) and "inutile" (useless) show that his efforts will have no outcome</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>3) </main>
				<text>The future participle "moriturus" (about to die) shows that his fate is certain - there's no way that he'll win.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>4) </main>
				<text>And yet he tries! We repect him, but also pity him as furor takes hold of him</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>3</number>
		<note>Lines 512 - 514</note>
		<latin>aedibus in mediis nudoque sub aetheris axe // ingens ara fuit iuxtaque veterrima laurus // incumbens arae atque umbra complexa penates.</latin>
		<english> In the middle of the palace, beneath the open // vault of heaven, was a huge altar and, nearby, a very ancient bay tree // overhanging the alter and embracing the household gods with its shade.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Q: How is the importance of the altar highlighted?</main>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>1) </main>
				<text>The alter seems directly connected to the gods, being under the "naked vault of heaven"</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>2) </main>
				<text>The alter is "ingens" (huge) - a significant feature of the household</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>3) </main>
				<text>It is in the "mediis aedibus" - at the centre of the most sacred building of Troy</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>4) </main>
				<text>The "penates" are there - the household gods</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>5) </main>
				<text>The superlative adjective "veterrima" shows how long the sacred laurel tree has been providing its shade (umbra)</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>4</number>
		<note>Lines 515 - 517</note>
		<latin>hic Hecuba et natae nequiquam altaria circum, // praecipites atra ceu tempestate columbae, // condensae et divum amplexae simulacra sedebant.</latin>
		<english>Hecuba and her daughters sat, pressed closely together in vain // around the altar and embracing the images of the gods, like doves driven // headlong like a black storm.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>nequiquam (in vain): </main>
				<text>we find out in a word that the alter will not protect them (dramatic irony)</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Hecuba and her daughters: </main>
				<text> They sre sticking together (condensae) and vulnerable (huddles at the alter for protection). They show pietas by touching the statues of the gods and trustuing their power. This image is also one of helpleness.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Dove similie: </main>
				<text>The daughters of Priam are innocent and pure, like the symbol o the white dove. We feel a surge of pitt for them - they are the collateral damage of war. The black storm is Death and Destructuion in the shape of the Greek army.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>5</number>
		<note>Lines 518 - 520</note>
		<latin>ipsum autem sumptis Priamum iuvenalibus armis // ut vidit, 'quae mens tam dira, miserrime coniunx, // impulit his cingi telis? aut quo ruis?' inquit.</latin>
		<english>However, when [Hecuba] saw Priam himself having put on youthful arms (weapons), she said "What purpose so dreadful, most wretched husband, has driven (you) to gird youself with these weapons? Or where are you rushing off to?</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>dira mens: </main>
				<text>a-mens, de-mens (like dementia) - these are ways of describing the loss of rational pious thought which result in Furor. Hecuba tries gently to pull Priam back from this</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Rheutorical questions: </main>
				<text> The questions are rhetorical - they are posed in order to have an emotional impact, not to find information. Hecuba is trying to make Priam pause for thought and break him out of Furor.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>6</number>
		<note>Lines 521 - 522</note>
		<latin>non tali auxilio nec defensoribus istis // tempus eget; non, si ipse meus nunc adforet Hector.</latin>
		<english>The circumstances do not need such aid now that sort of defenders; no, (not even) if my Hector himself were now present.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Hector: </main>
				<text>Hecuba remind Priam of Hector, their brave son who embodied Pietas, who was killed by Achilles. This will have a big emotional impact on Priam.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>talis, istis: </main>
				<text>Help 'like this' is a little disparaging, but is meant to wake Priam up to the reality of what he is doing, and, in reality, how much he can actually help (not at all)</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>7</number>
		<note>Lines 523 - 525</note>
		<latin>huc tandem concede; haec ara tuebitur omnes, // aut moriere simul.' sic ore effata recepit // ad sese et sacra longaevum in sede locavit.</latin>
		<english>Please come here; this altar will guard everyone, or you will die // together (with me)." Having uttered this from her mouth, she drew the // aged man to herself and places him on the sacred throne.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Hecuba's appeal to Priam </main>
				<text>is voiced in terms of togetherness and family - either the gods will protect us, or at least we will all die together</text>
			</point>
			<pint>
				<main>Recepti, locavit: </main>
				<text>She looks after him with gentle love and puts him on the throne (sacre sede). This is respectful. But she still gegs jer way so it is her strength and logic which prevails.</text>
			</pint>
		</notes>
	</section>
</page>