<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Aeneid: Lines 526-543</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>506-525.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 506-525</text>
		</link>
		<link>
			<url>544-559.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 544 - 559</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<section>
		<number>1</number>
		<note>Lines 526 - 529</note>
		<latin>ecce autem elapsus Pyrrhi de caede Polites, \\ unus natorum Priami, per tela, per hostes \\ porticibus longis fugit et vacua atria lustrat \\ saucius</latin>
		<english>However, behold, Polites, one of the sons of Priam, having escaped from the carnage of Pyrrhus, flees aling the long corridors through the weapons, through the enemy and traverses the empty halls, wounded.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Lines 525, 527 spondaic rhythm: </main>
				<text>Here, the slow rhythm reflects the painful progress of the wounded man. To make things worse, the corridors are "longis" (long) and there is no help in the "vacua" (empty) atriums.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Asyndetic "per": </main>
				<text>The structure here emphasises the density of the foes and weapons that he has faced; row upon row of hazards</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Enjambement: </main>
				<text>(One line continues into another) The word "saucius" (wounded) is held over to the next line, showing how Polites is limping with uncertain steps towards his goal.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>2</number>
		<note>Lines 529 - 530</note>
		<latin>illum ardens infesto vulnere Pyrrhus // insequitur, iam iamque manu tenet et premit hasta.</latin>
		<english>Pyrrhus, fired up, pursues him with a threatening wound, now, now holds him with his hand and presses upon him with his spear.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>ardens: </main>
				<text>Like "furor", the opposite of Pietas. Pyrrhus is thirsty for a kill and is chasing Polites in a maniacal way. Ethically, we should not approve.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>iam, iamque: </main>
				<text>Now, now - the repitition emphasises just how close Pyrrhus is to grabbing Polites. Virgil tries to keep the reader on the edge of their seat.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>530 dactylic rhythm: </main>
				<text>Energetic rhythm as Pyrrhus gallops down the corridor eager to finish Polites off. Echoes the adrenaline rush they must both have.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>3</number>
		<note>Lines 531 - 532</note>
		<latin>ut tandemante oculos evasit et ora parentum, // concidit ac multo vitam cum sanguine fudit.</latin>
		<english>Finally, when he came out before the eyes and faces of his parents, he fell down and poured out his life with a lot of blood.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Ironic pathos: </main>
				<text>At last (tandem) he is safe; and them he dies :-(. Hope destroyed by reality.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>fudit: </main>
				<text>(pour) a violent word - Polites doen't slowly bleed out, the blood gushes from him.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>oculos, ora: </main>
				<text>(eyes, face) Verbal redundancy (both aren't needed), but this emphasises the terrible situation and that it is happening in front of his parents.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>4</number>
		<note>Lines 533 - 534</note>
		<latin>hic Priamus, quamquam in media iam morte tenetur, // non tamen abstinuit nec voci iraeque pepercit:</latin>
		<english>Hereupon, Priam, although he was now in the midst of death, did not hold back, however, nor did he spare his voice and anger:</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>quamquam, tamen: </main>
				<text>(although, however) These both highlight the risk to Priam's safety he is taking by adressing Pyrrhus</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>voc, iraeque: </main>
				<text>The voise and anger are juxtaposed and elided ad Priam's whole body and voice become anger. He transforms into "Furor". (NB: Elison: two words are melded together when vowels meet)</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>5</number>
		<note>Line 535 - 539</note>
		<latin>'at tibi pro scelere,' exclamat, 'pro talibus ausis // di, si qua est caelo pietas quae talia curet, // persolvant grates dignas et praemia reddant // debita, qui nati coram me cernere letum // fecisti et patrios foedasti funere vultus.</latin>
		<english>"Well then," he shouted, "in return for your wickedness, in return for such presumption, if there is any righteousness in heaven to care for such things, may the gods render you fitting thanks and pay back the rewards due (to you), who have made me behold the death of my son in my presence and defiled a father's countenance with death.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>talibus, talia: </main>
				<text>The polypteton emphasises the contempt implied by 'such' when Priam refers to 'such deeds' of Pyrrhus.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>coram: </main>
				<text>The horror of his son's death amplified by being right in front of his parents.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>539 Alliteration: </main>
				<text>(last line) The repeated 'f' is a fricative consonant which shows frustration and anger - mirrors Priams feelings perfectly</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>persolvant, reddant: </main>
				<text>These are jussive passive subjunctives (jussive: acts like an order) - these are (respectful) commands and expresses Priam's will that Pyrrhus will be punished.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Pietas: </main>
				<text>Note the appearence of this key term. It is Right and Justfor Pyrrhus to get comeuppance (what he deserves)</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>6</number>
		<note>Line 540 - 543</note>
		<latin>at non ille, satum quo te mentiris, Achilles // talis in hoste fuit Priamo; sed iura fidemque // supplicis erubit corpusque exsangue sepulcro // reddidit Hectoreum meque in mea regna remisit".</latin>
		<english>But he, Achilles, from whom you falsly claim that you are sprung, was not such a person (as you) in the case of this enemy Priam; but he respected the rights and trust of the suppliant, gave back the bloodless body of Hector for burial and sent me back to my kingdom".</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>mentiris: </main>
				<text>"You lie when you say that you are his son" - this is an insult to cast doubt in Pyrrhus' mind and to hurt him.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>supplicis: </main>
				<text>A 'suppliant' is someone who appeals to the mercy of their conqueror. They submit themselves to the mercy of the winner, and then they MUST be treated with mercy (or invoke the displeasure of Jupiter). Refered to via "iura"</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>corpus sepulcro reddidit: </main>
				<text>Hugely important for the body to recieve a proper burial, or the dead sould may not be able to cross the Styx and enter the underworld</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
</page>