<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Aeneid: Lines 544-558</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>526-543.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 526-543</text>
		</link>
		<link>
			<url>705-720.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 705-720</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<section>
		<number>1</number>
		<note>Lines 544 - 546</note>
		<latin>sic fatus senior telumque imbelle sine ictus // coniecit, rauco quod protinus aere repulsum, // et summo clipei nequiquam umbone pependit.</latin>
		<english>The old man spoke thus and threw a feeble spear without any force, which was immediatly repelled by the harsh-sounding bronze and hung futilely from the surface of the boos (the centre bit) of the shield.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>545 Spondaic rhythm: </main>
				<text>The slow rhythm reflects the effot that the old man expends in trying to attack and the weakness behind it (without, ictus)</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>545 Alliteration: </main>
				<text>The letters C and Q bring out the clang of metal as the spear is successfully defended. (repulsum)</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Imbelle: </main>
				<text>Literally "unwarlike" - the old man does not brandish the weapon like a young warrior</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Nequiquam: </main>
				<text>Compare to line 510 and 515 when Priam pulls on his sword "pointlessly" and the daughters sat at the alter "in vain". Shows how is efforst are ultimatly worthless.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>2</number>
		<note>Lines 547 - 550</note>
		<latin>cui Pyrrhus: "referes ergo heac et nuntius ibis // Pelidae genitori. ille mea tristia facta // degeneremque Neoptolemum narrare memento. // nunc morere."</latin>
		<english>You will relate to these events, then, and will go as a messenger to my father, son of Peleus. Remember to tell him about my cruel deeds and about Neoptolemus, unworthy of his parentage. Now die.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>referes, ibis: </main>
				<text>Very menacing future indicatives. Not 'in the event of death' but 'you will take' (and die). He is almost setting out what he wants Priam to do and confirming his fate.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'mea tristia facta', 'degenerem': </main>
				<text>This self-deprecation is completely sarcastic. He is taunting Priam before he kills him, which is psychotic and twisted. Although perhaps explicable as a Furor-based reaction to Priam's curses</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>nunc morere: </main>
				<text>A chilling and cold and concise and brutal speech, His fate is certain.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>3</number>
		<note>Lines 550 - 553</note>
		<latin>hoc dicens altaria ad ipsa trementem // traxit et in multo lapsantem sanguine nati, // implicuitque comam laeva, dextraque coruscum // extulit ac lateri capulo tenus abdidit ensem.</latin>
		<english>While he was saying this, he dragged to the very alter the tremblinh (Priam), slipping in the copious blood of his son, grasped his hair with his left hand, while with his right hand he lifted up his glittering sword and buried it up to the hilt in Priam's side.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>ipsa: </main>
				<text>The 'very same' alter where Hecuba sought refuge - imagine how terrified they must be, about to watch her father/their father be brutally murdered. They're not safe anymore.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>trementem: </main>
				<text>Attention is drawn to Priam's age and fear - he is a vulnerable and helpless target.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>traxit: </main>
				<text>This is aggressive and physically violent. None of this is necessary to defeat a weak old man (overkill).</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>in sanguine nati: </main>
				<text>What more disgusting and horrific experience than being f=dragged through your own murdered son's blood? Again, highlights the cruelty and 'overkill'-ness of the situation that Pyrrhus is almost making a show out of.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>laeva, dextra: </main>
				<text>Left and rights hands juxtaposed to emphasise the full activity of the violence Pyrrhus is engaged in.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>comam: </main>
				<text>Yanking him up by the hair is undignified. Furthermore, he is an old man!</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>coruscum: </main>
				<text>The sword is described as "glittering" - this brings colour and movement to a grim scene. It makes the death scene seem glamorous and be enjoying. As humans, we are naturally interestes and fascinated by scenes of death e.g. slowing down to look at an accident on a motorway. We aren't expecting to see everyone OK, are we?</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>abdidit: </main>
				<text>"Buries" the blade up to the hilt. More super unnecessary overkill as Pyrrhus delivers a ton of Furor after the comments about his father.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>4</number>
		<note>Lines 545 - 558</note>
		<latin>haec finis Priami fatorum, hic exitus illum // sorte tulit Troiam incensam et prolapsa videntem // Pergama, tot quondam populis terrisque superbum // regnatorem Asiae. iacet ingens litore truncus, // avulsumque umeris caput et sine nomine corpus.</latin>
		<english>This (was) the end of Priam's fate, this death carried him off with accordance to his destiny, as he saw Troy set on fire and the citadel fallen down, (a man who was) once the proud ruler of so many people and land of Asia. He lies on the shore, a huge trunck, his head torn from his shoulders and a corpse without a name.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Q: What is dramatic about this last view we have of Priam?</main>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>"videntem pergama prolapsa": </main>
				<text>As he dies he is watching his beloved city which he rules over and help build up collapse into nothing. What a sad last sight.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>The contrast </main>
				<text>is striking between power when alive (once the proud ruler of) and his lack of recognition when dead (sine nomine corpus)</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>The 'truncus' (trunck): </main>
				<text>"With the head torn off" is a very dehumanising - his power is gone with his name, but also even his recognisable human shape.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>His previous power </main>
				<text>is emphasised with the intensifier "tot" (such...)</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>"fatorum" and "sorte": </main>
				<text>(fate) These underline how powerless mortals are to change the destiny provided to us by the gods. A recurrent theme in ancient literature. (NB: The Fates in Roman mythology are known as the "parcae")</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
</page>