<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Aeneid: Lines 705-720</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>544-558.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 544-558</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<section>
		<number>1</number>
		<note>Lines 705 - 706</note>
		<latin>dixerat ille, et iam per moenia clarior ignis // auditur, propiusque aestus incendia volvunt.</latin>
		<english>(Anchises) finishes speaking, and now the fire was heard more loudly throught the fortifications, and the fires rolled the heat nearer.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Impending menace: </main>
				<text>The approaching thre`at is presented well with the use of the comparative forms - clarior, propius. The power of the fire is such that it can be heard from the other side of the wall.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>2</number>
		<note>Lines 707 - 711</note>
		<latin>"ergo age, care pater, cervici imponere nostrae; // ipse subito umeris nec me labor iste gravabit; // quo res cumque cadent, unum et commune periclum, // una salus ambodus erit. mihi parvus Iulus sit comes, et longe servet vertigia coniunx.</latin>
		<english>(Aneas said) "Come then, dear father, place yourself on my neck; I myself will take (you) upon my shoulders, and that task will not burden me; however things turn out, both of us will have one and the same shared danger, (and) the same deliverance. Let little Iulus be my companion, and let my wife observe my footmarks at a distance.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>'care pater' (dear father): </main>
				<text>The way he addresses his father shows love and respect.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'ipse' (myself): </main>
				<text>This is an important duty and he will take care of it personally.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'nec labore gravabit' (nor will the work weight me down): </main>
				<text>Aeneas makes his father feel better by saying that it won't be any trouble - Pietas</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'una', 'unum' (one): </main>
				<text>The polyptoton of 'one' further enhances the feeling of loyalty and togetherness as Aneas assured his dad that he will not leave him behind.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'umeris' (shoulders), 'cervici' (neck): </main>
				<text>The direct physical nature of the support here is stricking. Aeneas will literally carry his father through the flames.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Pietas involves the whole family/community.</main>
				<text>There is an issue with Creusa and 'longe' (at a distance), but perhaps this is because she can look after herself more than the others. Furthermore, Aeneas may be seperating Creausa from his group so they are less likely to be spotted by the Greeks.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>3</number>
		<note>Lines 712 - 716</note>
		<latin>vos, famuli, quae dicam animis advertite vestris. // est urbe egressis tumulus templumque vetustum // desertae Cereris, iuxtaque antiqua cupressus // religione patrum multos servata per annos; // hanc ex diverso sedem veniemus in unam.</latin>
		<english>You, my family, heed to what I am going to say in your minds. As you leave the city, there is a mound and an old temple of deserted Ceres, and nearby, an ancient cypress, preserved for many years by the religious feeling of our fathers; it is to this same place that we shall come from different directions.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>'desertae Cereris' (of deserted Ceres): </main>
				<text>The goddess of plenty and harvest has been neglectes, and the corresponsing life-force of Troy has erroded.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'servata religione patrum' (religious feelings of our fathers): </main>
				<text>Pietas - religious care - so well sustained by the previous generations, has suffered. Aeneas must embody it for a new generation.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Line 713 alliteration ('est urbe ... vetustum'): </main>
				<text>The 't's make the details of his precise instructions easier to remember. And suggesting urgency - a ticking clock before Troy burns to the ground.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'et diverso in unam': </main>
				<text>They will come together from different locations (moving in seperate groups as to not be noticed), but also from different social backgrounds. These events are leveling them - royalty and servants are now working together.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>4</number>
		<note>Lines 717 - 720</note>
		<latin>tu, genitor, cape sacra manu patriosque penates; // me bello e tanto digressum et caede recenti // attrectare nefas, donec me flumine vivo // abluero".</latin>
		<english>You, father, take the sacred vessels and our fathers' household gods in your hand; (it is) a sin for me, having come from such a great war and recent slaughter, to touch them until I have washed my hands in running water".</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>'sacra' (sacred), 'penates' (household gods): </main>
				<text>The 'penates' are little statues of the household gods. Patrios - they've been in the family for a long time. They represent the Piety (and also safety) of the whole house.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'nefas attrectare': </main>
				<text>"it is ethically wrong for me to touch the penates" - a specific aspect of Pietas here is that it is wrong to come from killing to handling these religious objects before cleansing first.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'flumine vivo' (a live/running stream): </main>
				<text>The water has to be 'vivo' (alive, i.e. flowing) to cleans the soul of the person in the right way. WIth everything that's going on, Aeneas still bothers to get these things right.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
</page>