<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Aeneid: Lines 721-740</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>705-720.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 705-720</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<section>
		<number>1</number>
		<note>Lines 705 - 706</note>
		<latin>haec fatus latos umeros subieactaque colla // veste super fulvique insternor pelle leonis, // succedoque oneri;</latin>
		<english>Having spoken these (words), I cover my broad shoulders and my lowered neck with a garment top, the skin of  tawny lion, and take up the burden;</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>pelle lionis (skin of lion): </main>
				<text>The associetion here is with Hercules. They are the same but different. Yes, Aeneas has to be strong like Hercules, but he also has the family/community to think of as well. Modern Hercules.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Latos umeros (broad shoulders): </main>
				<text>Physically broad shoulders, but also conveying the other meaning of someone who is shouldering a burden of responsibility.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Subiectia, succedo (take up): </main>
				<text>(succedo - subcedo) The prefix is the same in both cases: "sub" = under, below. Aeneas shows humility as he lowers himself before the needs of others.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>2</number>
		<note>Lines 723-725</note>
		<latin>dextrae se parvus Iulus // implicuit sequiturque patrem non passibus aequis; // pone subit coniunx.</latin>
		<english>Little Iulus entwined himself in my right hand and followed his father with unequal steps; my wife followed behind.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>parvus, non passibus aequis: </main>
				<text>Iulus is shown to be especially vulnerable, described as 'parvus' (small). Our empathy is evoked more for Aeneas when we see that he is having to look after people who cannot look after themselves. This is further enhanced by "implicuit se dextrae" (entwined with my hand) - Iulus is not just holding his Dad's hand, but clinging to it for safety and dear life.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>3</number>
		<note>Lines 725-729</note>
		<latin>fermiur per opaca locorum, // et me, quem dudum non ulla iniecta movebant // tela neque adverso glomerati examine Grai, // nunc omnes terrent aurae, sonus excitat omnis // suspensum et pariter comitique onerique timentem.</latin>
		<english>We are bourne along through shady places, and I, who not long ago was unmoved by any weapons thrown (at me) or by the Greeks, massed together in an opposing thong, was now terrified by ever breeze, scared by every noise, wavering and fearing for both companion and burden alike.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Aneas' state of mind as an expression of Pietas: </main>
				<text></text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Line 727 farming similie: </main>
				<text>"glomerati examine" (massed together in an opposing thong): like bees massed together in a swarm. Virgil grew up on a farm and would be very familiar with how angry bees behaved when they were threatened.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Line 728 spondaic: </main>
				<text>They make slow progress as Aeneas looks around to check for every hazard</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Line 728 balance: </main>
				<text>omnes-verb-noun-noun-verb-omnis: the enclosing "omnis/omnes" emphasises the threat on every side. The symmetic balance shows how their fortunes balance on a knife-edge, and that he fears every sound/sight in equal measure.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>4</number>
		<note>Lines 730-732</note>
		<latin>iamque propinquabam portis omnemque videbar // evasisse viam, subito cum creber ad aures // visus adesse pedum sonitus, ...</latin>
		<english>And now I was approaching the gates and seemed to have passed the whole route, when suddenly the frequent sound of feet seemed to come to my ears, ...</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Drama and Suspense: </main>
				<text></text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Compare Polites: </main>
				<text>He was so close to safety, but was killed by Pyrrhus - relatable to his situation now.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Line 730 alliteration: </main>
				<text>The plosives reflect Aneas' physical exertion as he carries his Dad, his quickened heartbeat and anxiety takes over.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Lines 731/732 sibilance: </main>
				<text>The menacing threat of the approaching enemy slithers through the narrative.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Line 732 dactylic: </main>
				<text>The urgent drumming of the feat/hooves show how close the Greeks are to finding them.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>5</number>
		<note>Lines 732-734</note>
		<latin>genitorque per umbram // propiciens 'nate,' exclamat, 'fuge, nate; propinquant. // ardentes clipeos atque aera micantia cerno.'</latin>
		<english>... and my father, looking ahead through the shade, shouted 'Son, flee, son; they are approaching. I percieve glowing shields and flashing bronze.'</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Anchises' direct speach:</main>
				<text></text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Very exciting </main>
				<text>to have Aneas' Dad spot the glowing metal as it reflects from the fire. Builds up tension - Aneas didn't see them. He's too focused on his Dad. The flowing from the fire percieves the Greeks as demons from hell, or divine beings. This could also reflect Anchises' warning earlier about wanting to be left behind, and 'we share one fate'</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Repetition </main>
				<text>of 'son' (nate) emphasises Anchises' fear.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>'ardentes' (fiery) </main>
				<text>suggests both Furor of the Greeks and the physical destruction of Troy</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>6</number>
		<note>Lines 735 - 736</note>
		<latin>hic mihi nescio quod trepido male numen amicum // confusam eripuit mentem.</latin>
		<english>Thereupon, some evil divine spirit snatched away my confused mind panic-sticken.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Aneas' state of mind: </main>
				<text></text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Line 735 dactylic: </main>
				<text>the agitation here is in the rhythm as Aneas' mind is broken by "evil spirits" (numen) which embodies all the stress of responsibility and danger of their surroundings.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>7</number>
		<note>Lines 737-740</note>
		<latin>dum sequor et nota excedo regione viarum, // hau misero coniunx fatone erepta Creusa // substitit, erravitne via seu lapsa resedit, // incertum; nec post oculis est reddita nostris.</latin>
		<englis>For a while I followed the byways at a run, and left the known area if the roads, alas, whether my wife Creusa, snatched away from me in my misery by destiny, stopped, or wandered off the road or, falling, sat down, is unknown; she was not restored afterwards to my sight.</englis>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>avia, viarum, via (byways, path): </main>
				<text>the polyptoton here brings focus to the idea of the right of way. Aneas is physically lost, but also metaphorically lost - he doesn't know the right way forward for his people, and this is distressing.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>fato-ne, erravit-ne (fate, wander): </main>
				<text>The repeated questions highlights his confusion and disorientation.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Panic and shame: </main>
				<text>Aneas has a Pietas crisis as he realises that he was unable to protect them all. He describes himself as "misero" (miserable) because of this.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>substitit (stop): </main>
				<text>a stuttering dactyl mirrors Creusa's possible faultering steps, and maybe Aneas' sobs or stuttering in misery.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>"incertum" (unknown): </main>
				<text>This word is enjambed onto line 740 and is placed emphatically at the beginning - it sums Aneas' state of mind perfectly. He is not sure what is going on, where she has gone, or what is demanded by fate (fato).</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Listing options: </main>
				<text>Emphasises the wildness and panic-stricken mind - he is trying everything to desperatly find a potential solution.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>"nec reddita" (not returned): </main>
				<text>Shows his desperation - he is searching and putting himself at risk. He hoped it was a joke, or he'd manage to fiend her; but he realises that he cannot.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
</page>