<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Aeneid: Lines 768-779</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>721-740.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 721-740</text>
		</link>
		<link>
			<url>780-794.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 780-794</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<section>
		<number>1</number>
		<note>Lines 768 - 770</note>
		<latin>ausus quin etiam voces iactare per umbram // implevi clamore vias, maestusque Creusam // nequiquam ingeminans iterumque iterumque vocavi.</latin>
		<english>Nay, having dared even to hurl cries through the shadow(s), I filled the streets with shouting and sorrowfully repeating (the name) Creusa in vain, I called her again and again.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>"ausus quin etiam": (Nay, having dared) </main>
				<text>By shouting he is daring because this sound may alert the Greek soldiers of his presence. "quin etiam" (having dared) suggests that he understands this risk, but proceeds anyway.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>"implevi visas" (filled the streets): </main>
				<text>This highlights the volume of Aneas' shouts - he is desperate to find his wife. The echo this would create is illustrated in "iterumque iterumque" and the repitition of 'v's in "impleVi ... Vias".</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Repitition of "iterumque": </main>
				<text>The word 'again' is squared producing a hyberbolic resonance (gauge emotions of reader). Highlights his hopeless desperation.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>"nequiquam" (in vain): </main>
				<text>This is a recurring term in book 2 and emphasises the futility of Aneas' actions (dramatic irony). Remember, Aneas is telling all of this to Dido, therefore he is dramatic ironising himself - irony is quite poignant (sad memory)</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>2</number>
		<note>Lines 771 - 773</note>
		<latin>quaerenti et tectis urbis sine fine ruenti // infelix simulacrumatque ipsius umbra Creusae // visa mihi ante oculos et nota maior imago.</latin>
		<english>As I was searching for her and rushing without end through the dwellinga of thie city, the unhappy ghost and shade of Creusa herself appeared to me before my eyes.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>quaerenti (searching), ruenti (rushing): </main>
				<text>Two present participles. These show how Aneas is panicking and trying to do everything at once, instead of the calm ordered thinking which the situation requires.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>sine fine (without end): </main>
				<text>suggests (a) that he would never stop looking for Creusa and (b) that he may have been running in circles in his upset/panicked state.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>simulacrum (replica), umbra (shadow), imago (image): </main>
				<text>These words all refer to the same thing - a ghost (therefore verbal redundancy): the shock of seeing something as unusual as a ghost merits several labels! It is as if Dido did not believe Aneas the first time he said it. Perhaps he does not know how to describe the ghost as it's so unusual?</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>ante oculos (before my eyes): </main>
				<text>verbal redundancy; this is not required after "she appeared". It would have been difficult for him to believe his eyes and therefore acts as emphasis and shock.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>nota maior (taller than I would have known her): </main>
				<text>the account of a ghost encounter would be strange - the details are designed to disorient and upset you.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>3</number>
		<note>Lines 774 - 775</note>
		<latin>obstipui, steruntque comae et vox faucibus haesit. // tum sic adfari et curas his demere dictis:</latin>
		<english>I was astounded, my hairs stood on end and my voice stuck in my throat. Then she addressed my as follows and removed my anxieties (cares) with these words:</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>obstipui (shocked): </main>
				<text>The early caesura reflects how Aneas is cut off abruptly in the middle of his actions by the sheer shock of what he sees.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>comae, vox (hairs, voice): </main>
				<text>Virgil describes the physical symptoms of shock, as the hairs stand up on Aneas' skin and his voice gets stuck in his throat. Aneas is super confident and a rouding speach maker (adress to troops in book II), so losing the ability to speak is a significant reaction.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>adfari, demere: </main>
				<text>These are infinitive acting main verbs - they are noticeable and have a blunter, more direct force compared to a normal main verb.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Creusa shows Pietas: </main>
				<text>(adfari, curas) she tries to take away his cares (anxieties, worries). This is very considerate showing that Creusa is an example of Pietas just like Aneas. See 'Pieta' by Michelangelo.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>4</number>
		<note>Lines 776 - 779</note>
		<latin>'quid tantum insano iuvat indulgere dolori, // o dulcis coniunx? non haec sine numine divum // eveniunt; nec te comiten hinc portare Creusam // fas, aut ille sinit superi regnator Olympi.'</latin>
		<english>'How does it help to indulge so much in mad grief, O sweet husband? These things do not occur without the will of the gods; nor is it destined for you to take Creusa here as your companion, now does the great ruler of high Olympus allow it.'</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Creusa's tone: </main>
				<text>Her tone her is didactic (teacher-like), firm, and even slightly reprimanding in the first line. The firm tone usually helps to calm down a panicking individual.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>"O sweet husband" (O dulcis coniunx): </main>
				<text>This takes the harsh edge off this by showing heartfelt, gentle affection.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>So how does she take away Aneas' cares?</main>
				<text></text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main></main>
				<text>Assures him that her death isn't his fault but rather the will of the gods. He may have been starting to blame himself for not looking after her better.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main></main>
				<text>The clarity of 'Jupiter's plan' will help to guide him, and it's easier to hear this from someone he knows and loves.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
</page>