<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="style.xsl"?>
<page>
	<title>Aeneid: Lines 780-794</title>
	<doclinks>
		<link>
			<url>768-779.xml</url>
			<text>Lines 768-779</text>
		</link>
	</doclinks>
	
	<section>
		<number>1</number>
		<note>Lines 780 - 782</note>
		<latin>'longa tibi exsilia vastum maris aequor arandum, // et terram Hisperiam venies, ubi Lydius arva // inter opima virum leni fuit agmine Thybis.</latin>
		<english>'You will have a long exile, and must plough the vast expanse of the sea; you will come to the land of the west, where the Lydian Thybis flows with it's gentle course between the rich plowed fields of men.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>longs exsilia (long exile): </main>
				<text>Creusa is honest and direct with the bad news. Anaes will be wondering homeless for a long time, with the plural form of "exsilia" emphasisng this.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>arandum (must plough): </main>
				<text>The gerundive expresses obligation: Aneas has no choice. 'Ploughing' the sea is an interesting metaphor. Seeds are sown in ploughed fields, which is hopeful. The work is hard, but the results are worth it.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>opima, leni: </main>
				<text>The River Tiber, Rome's lifeline, is a gentle (leni) and the land fertile (opima). Creusa gives the bad news but then balances it out with optimism about the future. Compare the language used to describe Po Vakkey after Hannibal's Trials (in Livy)</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>2</number>
		<note>Lines 783 - 784</note>
		<latin>illic res laetae regnumque et regia coniunx // parta tibi; lacrimas dilectae pelle Creusae.</latin>
		<english>There, joyful circumstances, a kingdom and a royal wife have been stored for you; banish your tears for your beloved Creusa.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>res laetae, regnum (happy circumstances, kingdom): </main>
				<text>'happy circumstance' cuggests peace. The facts however are totally different. When Aneas gets to Latium, he faces a difficult and bloody was against Turnus.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>regia coniunx (royal wife): </main>
				<text>This is Lavinia, King Latinus' daughter. She isn't simply there for the taking, but is promised to Turnus. Juno will stir up a war for Aneas. Creusa doesn't mention this, but perhaps she has not been informed of Juno's plan. The emotional impact here is huge: Aneas loves Creusa and now se is telling him, as he tried to process the fact of her death, that he will marry another woman.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>pelle lacrimas (dry your tears): </main>
				<text>Her saying this indirectly tells us that Aneas is crying.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Rhythm. </main>
				<text>Line 783 (illic ... coniunx) is completely spondaic. Creusa slows down the rhythm to announce the important prophecy.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<number>3</number>
		<note>Lines 785 - 787</note>
		<latin>non ego Myrmidonum sedes Dolopumve superbas // aspiciam aut Grais servitum metribus ibo, // Dardanis et divae Veneris nurus;</latin>
		<english>I shall not look upon the proud dwellings of the Myrmidons nor of the Dolopes, or go in order to be a slave to Greek matrons, I a descendant of Dardanus and the daughter-in-law of divine Venus;</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>superbas: (proud) </main>
				<text>we have seen the Greek arrogance in the figure of Pyrrhus. The Greeks are 'proud' to have won the war and will take prisoners as slaves.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>There is consolation </main>
				<text>for Aneas that Creusa will not suffer the disgrace of serving in the Greek's homes. She tries to ease this over the pain of her death.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Incomplete line (line 787): </main>
				<text>It would be outrageous for a descendant of Dardanus and a relative of Venus to be a slave. This outrage is reflected in the unusual truncated line ('truncus').</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>4</number>
		<note>Line 788</note>
		<latin>sed me magna deum genetrix his detinet oris.</latin>
		<english>but the great mother of the gods keeps me in these shores.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>the 'magna genetrix' (great mother): </main>
				<text>This referres to Cybele. She is an ancient Trojan deity associated with Mount Ida from where she lookes on in protection of the Trojans. Aneas exported her to Rome where worship is continued. Toung men would suffer castration as a mark of dedication to her.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Very similar rhetoric to Aneas </main>
				<text>when he explains to Dido that the gods made him leave Carthage.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>5</number>
		<note>Line 789</note>
		<latin>iamque vale et nati serva communis amorem.'</latin>
		<english>Now, farewell and preserve the love for the son we have in common.'</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>vale (stay strong): </main>
				<text>she means this (validus = strong) literally. Aneas needs to be a strong leader for his people and his family.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>serva amorem (for the love of our common son): </main>
				<text>their love will live on in the relationship between Aneas and Iulus. Another cause for optimism - she will always be there for him, in a way.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>6</number>
		<note>Lines 790 - 791</note>
		<latin>haec ubi dicta dedit, lacrimantem at multa volentem // dicere deseruit, tenusque recessit in auras.</latin>
		<english>When she had related these words, she left me weeping and wanting to say so many things, and withdrew into the slender breezes.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>lacrimantem (crying), volentem (saying): </main>
				<text>the use of present participles enhances the idea that Aneas was frustratingly cut off in the middle of his actions.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>in auras (into air): </main>
				<text>She disappears literally into thin air (in auras). This would be a great shock and very upsetting as he must have literally a thousand questions to ask.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
	<section>
		<number>7</number>
		<note>Lines 792 - 794</note>
		<latin>ter conatus ibi collo dare bracchia circum; // ter frustra comprensa manus effugit imago, // par levibus ventis volucrique simillima somno.</latin>
		<english>Three times I tried there to put my arms around her neck; three times the ghost which I grasped in vain escaped my hands, like the light winds and most similar to winged sleep.</english>
		<notes>
			<point>
				<main>Repetition of 'ter' (three times): </main>
				<text>along with 'frustra' (in vain) emphasises how drustrating it is for Aneas to want to embrace his wife but not be able to.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>collo </main>
				<text>brings to mind his father Anchises and how he wants to protect his family.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>simillima (most similar): </main>
				<text>the superlative form suggests how confused and bewildered he is - he can't tell the ghost apart, now whether the whole encounter is a dream.</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>winged sleep (volcri somno). </main>
				<text>This brings to mind the god 'Hypnos' (of sleep) who is pictured on a Greek vase depicting the death of Sarpedon</text>
			</point>
			<point>
				<main>Creusa is compared to a 'winged dream' </main>
				<text>because she flies away and because ANeas won't be sure that he hasn't been dreaming.</text>
			</point>
		</notes>
	</section>
</page>